<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb007">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theophilus Adam Wylie to Louisa Wylie Boisen, December 26, 1860</title>
            <author key="TAWylie">Theophius Adam Wylie</author>
            <!-- what about when two authors-->
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded By</resp>
               <name>Katherine Frawley</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Indiana University</publisher>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title key="EB007" type="letter">Theophilus Adam Wylie to Louisa Wylie Boisen, December 26, 1860</title>
               <!-- what is the n ?!?!-->
               <author key="TAWylie">Theophilus Adam Wylie</author>
               <persName type="addressee" key="Louisa">Louisa Wylie Boisen</persName>
               <date when="1860-12-26">December 26, 1860</date>
            </bibl>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Wylie House Repository, Indiana University</repository>
                  <collection>Theophilus Adam Wylie Family Correspondence</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents><p>Document is 4 pages, handwritten on recto and verso</p></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="compositon" unit="page" quantity="4">4 pages</measure>
                           <!-- what is composition? should i change it based on each letter, since some use leafs and others use pages -->
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc hands="1">
                     <handNote xml:id"TAWylie">Handwritten by Theophilus Adam Wylie</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" xml:id="EB007" n="##" facs="EB007c">
               <!-- MIGHT WANT THIS ONE FIRST, BEFORE FULL TRANSCRIPTION -->
               <head type="LIZZIE_REFERENCE"/>
               <p>"Lizzie is going home today to spend her holidays. So Ma and I will have to get up to make the pies."</p>
               <!-- WHAT HAPPENS WHEN MULTIPLE REFERENCES? ADD AN ADDED <P> WITH A [...]??? -->
           </div>
           <div type="letter" xml:id="EB007" n="##" facs="EB007a">
            <head type="FULL_TRANSCRIPTION"/>
            <!-- WHAT IS THIS? THE TEMPLATE HAS THE TYPE = RAW, AND THE NEXT ONE = EDIT...  -->
            <opener>
               <dateline> 
                  <placeName>Bloomington, Indiana</placeName>
                  <date>Dec 26th 1860</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Lou</salute>
               <!-- <salute> Dear <persName> Lou </persName> -->
            </opener>            
            <p>I was much pleased yesterday in hearing from Dr. H. of your improvement in health and I think from his representations that if you are prudent that you will soon be yourself again. 
            Yesterday the children had their rejoicing over their Christmas gifts. The stockings were all duly suspended on Monday Evening and their treasures examined the next morning. It seems to me that the happiness it gives the little ones compensates for the folly of the custom. The Old S. Presbyterians had a Xtmas tree in Dunn's hall and the Sabbath school assembled there to receive its decorations. So you see how old Popish customs are sanctioned</p>
            <pb facs="EB007b"></pb>
            <p>and observed by grave Protestant Presbyterians. You remember the story told of John Bunyan. Somebody, knowing his hatred of every thing Popish, in order to vex him when in jail sent him a present of a Christmas pie. John eat the pie and sent back word to the [one word] that he had lived long enough in this world to know the difference between Christmas and Pie. So it is with these customs, they have a popish name, but there is a good deal of difference between them and Popery. 
            Yesterday Dr. and Mrs. Dodds and Mr. and Mrs. McC and Redick dined with us. We had quite a pleasant time of it. Cousin Lizzie seems cheerful and much like her former self. I have been overhauling my papers and drawers and hardly know what is going on in this busy bustling world of Bloomington. I hear that Jake Young got a pretty severe rap over his head from some quarreling drunkards in his beer room. If it had killed him, it would hardly be pay for the evil he has done. Prof. Ballantine has gone to C to see his girls. Henry got home last Friday. I have seen him but once. He was living and well. 
            Whenever Dr H. thinks you have been long enough in C we will try and find some way of getting you home. I hope it will be before long, but don't you get uneasy or homesick or fidgety or blue or any thing of that sort. Take things coolly and practically and not sentimentally. We live in a world of realities and we must take things as they are not as we would wish them to be. You often regret the past and so do I, but I regret that I did not mingle more in society and take more fresh air and active exercise, as well as some other things that I need not mention. You—that you were such a naughty girl—it is well you told us of it or we would not have found it out. If you are wise, while not neglecting the "great concern" of all, you will improve your opportunity by mingling with different sorts of people, learning their ways, noticing what is good and worthy of imitation and what is bad and to be avoided. There is both pleasure and profit in this. If we are </p>
            <pb facs="EB007c"></pb>
            <p>pleased with the portraits we find in books of the great and good and amused with the comical, if we only knew how to observe, we would find characters equally entertaining though not perhaps so spicy as the novelist makes them in every day life. You need, as much as any one, some of that training that will enable you to mingle with different classes of people with ease and without any feeling of restraint. Lizzie is going home today to spend her holidays. So Ma and I will have to get up to make the pies. Mag and Dick are as usual. Phandy has got a pair of skates and he has been out the whole day with them. Brown thinks no one is able to teach him but you and Dory still amuses us with his uproariousness. 
            Present our kindest regards to Dr. H., Mrs. H. Miss D, and all the rest. If you feel dull and the Dr. says yes, take a walk. I have a notion to ask him to prescribe dancing to cure you. We all send our love and wishing you a happy New Year, I remain  </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate father</salute>
               <signed> T.A. Wylie</signed>
               <!-- COULD ALSO BE?? <SIGNED><PERSNAME KEY="PERSON">PERSONS NAME AS SIGNED </PERSONNAME></SIGNED>-->
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <note> Postscript is on lower left corner in TAW's handwriting </note>
               <p>Miss E. L. M. Wylie, Chicago</p>
            </postscript>
         </div> 
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
